Finding aid to the Margery Wells Steer papers SSC.MS.00180
Sophia Smith Collection
Margery Wells Steer papers
1938-1992
Sophia Smith Collection
Steer, Margery Wells
SSC.MS.00180
1.042 linear feet (3 containers)
Margery Wells Steer was a journalist and pacifist. Material includes correspondence with women's historian Mary Beard, with editors of Soviet Woman journal, and with Soviet women professors. Writings include her column, Peace and the People, published books, articles for Soviet Women, and a typescript of The Weight of a Snowflake. Other correspondents include her publisher, readers, and editor, as well as William Beard and Irma Drodina, Valentina Fedetova, Nelya Ramazanova, Margarita Smolyaninova, Olga Suslova, Olga Ushakova, and Galina Zlomanova.
Biographical / Historical
Margery Wells Steer was born in New Canaan, Connecticut, in 1899 and grew up on an eastern Long Island farm near Riverhead. She and her husband, James Steer, graduated from Oberlin College in 1923. They farmed near Youngstown, Ohio, from the early 1930s to 1963 while Mr. Steer taught school in Youngstown, and retired first to Atwood Lake, Ohio, and then to Friends House in Sandy Spring, Maryland.
The Steers have long been active on behalf of world peace. Mrs. Steer has published articles on historical and political subjects, edited community newsletters, and written columns. Her column, "Treating of This and That," appeared in the Journal of Education (Boston) between 1949 and 1951, and "Peace and the People" first in the Grove City Reporter Herald (PA) and continuing in Farm and Dairy (Salem, Ohio) from 1966 to the present. "Peace and the People" was written "to bring readers of a farm newspaper in northeastern Ohio and western Pennsylvania information on ways in which an individual can create peace." A compilation of her articles was published in 1956 under the title New Frontiers for Rural America. She also prepared a compilation of selected columns of "Peace and the People" entitled "The Weight of a Snowflake" (l966) which was never published. A volume of letters from foreign students who shared their home for varying periods of time was published under the title Dear Grandparents in 1981.
The Steers helped organize the Carroll County (Ohio) chapter of People to People International and opened their home to visitors under that program and the Experiment in International Living.
Scope and Contents
The Margery Wells Steer papers consist of her writings, correspondence, and some printed material.
The correspondence documents her relationship with Mary Beard and several Soviet women and also relates to her newspaper column. Of particular interest are the thirty-six letters from Mary Beard, 1950 to 1955. Steer wrote to her in 1950 requesting historical information, and the resulting friendship and exchange of letters continued until Mary Beard's death. These personal letters deal with a wide range of topics and are a reflection of Beard's many interests. Steer also corresponded with the English Edition editors of Soviet Woman between 1957 and 1985 and with two other Soviet women (1968; 1971-76), both of whom are professors at the University of Moscow. The correspondence about "Peace and the People" consists primarily of letters exchanged with her readers and with the editor of Farm and Dairy, also with other newspapers and publishers about the publication of her column.
The writings consist of the newspaper column "Peace and the People" (1966- 1986) and nine letters and articles published in Soviet Woman between 1971 and 1984. In addition there is a published copy of her book Dear Grandparents and a typescript of "The Weight of a Snowflake."
A few miscellaneous printed items are by and about Mary Beard.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Margery Wells Steer donated these papers beginning in 1966.
International education--History--Sources; Women journalists--United States--History--Sources; Peace movements--United States--History--Sources; Women--Soviet Union--History; Women and peace; Women--Periodicals; Soviet woman (Periodical); Grove City reporter-herald (Grove City, Pa.: Newspaper); Writings; correspondence; photographs; clippings; Youth of All Nations, Inc.; Steer, Margery Wells; Beard, Mary, 1876-1958--Correspondence; Beard, William, 1907- --Correspondence; Fedetova, Valentina--Correspondence; Ramazanova, Nelya--Correspondence; Smolyaninova, Margarita--Correspondence; Suslova, O.--Correspondence; Ushakova, Olga--Correspondence; Zlomanova, Galina--Correspondence; Drodina, Irma--Correspondence; Wilson, Alice Steer
- Series I. Writings
  - "Peace and the People"
    - Chronological list of columns, 1966-86 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clippings of column from the Grove City (PA) Reporter Herald and Free Press Standard (Carrollton, OH), 1966-70 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Clippings of column from Farm and Dairy (Salem, OH), 1966-86 (Box 1, Folder 3-9)
  - Soviet Woman: articles, 1971-84 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Other articles, 1951; undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dear Grandparents: Letters from around the World (Ardmore, PA: Dorrance & Co.), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The Weight of a Snowflake": unpublished typescript, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The View in Winter: A Book of Poems, 1992 (Box 2)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Mary Beard, 1951-55 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - William Beard, 1956-61; 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Peace and the People"
    - General, 1966-80 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    - Permissions and inquiries to possible publishers, 1965-85 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Margarita Smolyaninova, 1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Editors of Soviet Woman, English Edition
    - Olga Suslova and Olga Ushakova, 1957-72 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Olga Suslova and Valentina Fedetova, 1973-77 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Valentina Fedetova and Nelya Ramazanova, 1979-82 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Nelya Ramazanova and Irma Drodina, 1938-1989; undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Youth of All Nations, Inc. (pen pal program), New York Office, 1970-71 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Galina Zlomanova, 1971-76 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966; 1972-75 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Series III. Miscellaneous
  - Clippings by and about Mary Beard, 1950; undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Biographical material about Margery and James Steer, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- 2008 accession, Accession 2008-S-0101
  - View From the Window by Margery Wells Steer: poems, 1992
  - Note cards with excerpts and illustrations from the book, n.d.
  - A Family Chronicle: photocopy of table of contents, 1966